# Paul Hughes, MBA

Vice President - Business Attraction at Arizona Commerce Authority

HughesPJ@cox.net

# Summary

When you grow up as the 8th child out of nine, you learn how to compete. Later, you reflect on how amazing your parents were in raising all those hungry mouths on one salary. That "bootstrap" sentiment is likely the reason that I joined the best of the best, the US Marines, and later earned an MBA from Arizona State and then went on to complete the Entrepreneurship Development program at MIT.

I'm a strong believer in the power of a good brand and the elegance of smooth operations being executed by a closely knit team pulling in the same direction. It takes patience, but the final product is worth the wait.

As the COO of Guardian 8, we started with an idea and carried that all the way through to a product launch in early 2014. Everything needed to be built from scratch...product, trusted manufacturing partners, investor support, a quality team that exists to this day, and a brand that went from zero recognition among security professionals to over 70% in less than a year. I learned something about myself in my five years there: it's not what I do that matters to me, it's why I do it. Connecting with the mission of protecting others from pain, hunger, poverty or harm is essential for me.

When it's ready for public viewing, my next passion project - Enfuego Technologies - is going to blow away job seekers who are asked to cram all of their existence into a 2-page résumé and submit it blindly, only to get a rejection letter 30 seconds after hitting "submit". Coming soon!

# Experience

### Vice President - Business Attraction at Arizona Commerce Authority

February 2016 - Present (1 year 1 month)

Appointed as liaison to the Aerospace & Defense Subcommittee seated with twenty-one of the most influential industry executives in the state.

As your single point of contact, we will make it easy to access partners around the state as well as information, incentives, and a host of services including:

- •Confidential site-selection assistance
- •Customized research and analysis of tax, real estate, utility, and transportation costs
- Arranging meetings with officials, economic development professionals, workforce, and educational leaders
- •Workforce data, wage information and programs to help with hiring and training
- •Access to regulatory authorities; clarification of governmental regulations

•Access to Arizona regional and community partner information

### Founder at Enfuego Technologies LLC

May 2015 - Present (1 year 10 months)

Re-inventing how job seekers and employers connect through the development of a new SaaS platform that dynamically optimizes job seeker résumé content using factual data from your unique historical "word cloud" and filtering relevant job posts to 90% valid opportunity or higher.

### C.O.O. and Board Director at Guardian 8 Corporation

February 2010 - May 2015 (5 years 4 months)

Guardian 8 provides the professional security industry with professional grade personal defense and accountability systems. The company made its debut appearance at ASIS in Orlando in September 2011 and has won an Innovation of the Year award from the industry.

#### **Director - New Markets at TASER International**

March 2006 - November 2009 (3 years 9 months)

Developed the business plan and distribution approach for driving sales in a newly defined \$50M market segment. Responsible for speaking or presenting key concepts and program characteristics to elected officials, members of state correctional agencies, US Courts (Parole) and the Federal Bureau of Prisons.

- \* Ensure sales personnel understand high expectations and are properly skilled, equipped, and rewarded.
- \* Collaborate with 26 national distributors and dealers to enhance product advocacy.
- \* Crafted channel strategies in alignment with organizational objectives.
- \* Expanded sales pipeline by \$3,000,000 through client-specific strategies.
- \* Cultivated strong working relationships within State and Federal agencies.

#### **Board of Directors at Saddleback Communications**

2005 - 2007 (2 years)

Provided strategic guidance in the transition from POT (plain old telephone) service to fiber-optic bandwidth and wireless site leasing.

#### Corporal (E-4) at United States Marine Corps

September 1985 - September 1991 (6 years 1 month)

US MARINE CORPS - El Toro, California

Corporal (E-4): Honorably Discharged

Engaged in high risk, stressful operations while maintaining team cohesion and attaining mission objectives. Meritoriously promoted to each rank achieved. Decorated for combat action contributing to the liberation of Kuwait.

# Skills & Expertise

# **Product Management**

**Business Strategy** 

**Sales** 

**Managerial Finance** 

**Distribution Strategies** 

**Government Procurement** 

**Management Development** 

**Strategic Planning** 

Leadership

**Program Management** 

**Crisis Management** 

**Team Leadership** 

**Strategy** 

**Risk Assessment** 

**Surveillance** 

**Business Planning** 

**Training** 

**Security Management** 

**New Business Development** 

**Marketing** 

**Team Building** 

**Emergency Management** 

Management

**Entrepreneurship** 

**Physical Security** 

**Cross-functional Team Leadership** 

**Security** 

**Sales Management** 

Government

**Selling** 

**Private Investigations** 

**Sales Process** 

**Employee Training** 

**Corporate Security** 

**Recruiting** 

**Budgets** 

**Security Training** 

**Security Operations** 

Negotiation

**Public Speaking** 

**Operations Management** 

**Start-ups** 

**Business Development** 

**Competitive Analysis** 

**Marketing Strategy** 

### **Interests**

Professional Development: Executive education series offered at MIT.

Hobbies: Fly fishing, golf, ice hockey, downhill skiing.

Local politics.

## **Patents**

# Conditional use of an incapacitation device (CDPM).

**United States Patent** 

Inventors: Paul Hughes, MBA

### Education

# Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Sloan School of Management

EDP, Entrepreneurial Development, 2010 - 2010

#### **Penn State University**

Certificate, Non-Lethal Weapons: Policies, Procedures & Technologies, 2008 - 2008

#### **Arizona State University**

MBA, Global Management & Leadership, 2002 - 2004

Wauwatosa East High School

## **Publications**

# Security Force Management - Technology's Impact on Security

ASIS International June 9, 2014

Authors: Paul Hughes, MBA, Gary Kuty, Robert L Dodge, Robert Giordiano

A thorough understanding of the trends and issues affecting the management of a company and security officers is mandatory if you want to maintain a cutting-edge security program. Private security operations and officers have been powerfully impacted by the development of guidelines and standards, for example, as well as recent state and federal legislation and regulations.

Learn best practices for security operations. Examine the impact of stellar security officer management and see how recent industry changes and new strategies drive a more responsive and efficient security company into the future.

Sponsored by the ASIS Security Services Council

# Paul Hughes, MBA

Vice President - Business Attraction at Arizona Commerce Authority

HughesPJ@cox.net



# 3 person has recommended Paul

"I had the pleasure of getting to know Paul while he was at TASER. He was tasked with a very difficult assignment of building sales within the corrections sector for the company. I was very impressed with Paul's creativeness and commitment to growing this business. Adept at competing for scarce resources, he had the skill set to not only develop a plan but to execute the plan for success. As the VP of Consumer Sales for TASER, I recognize the importance of this to the sales process. The ability to both plan and execute while working with near autonomy earns Paul my highest recommendation. He would be a true asset to any sales organization."

— Ralf Engelbrecht, managed Paul indirectly at TASER International

"Paul Hughes reminds me of some of the most effective executives that I worked with at Intel Corporation, PepsiCo, and 5.11 Tactical - Paul can work at the CEO level, while constructively building the team, and working harder than anybody."

— Brent Jaramillo, worked indirectly for Paul at TASER International

"Paul is driven, results oriented, and has high standards of integrity."

— Eric Erickson, MBA, FACHE, studied with Paul at Arizona State University

Contact Paul on LinkedIn